Mss.973.N75 Mss.973.N75
American Philosophical Society
North American Land Company ledger, 1795-1805
Mss.973.N75
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet
The North Amercian Land Company ledger contains accounts with prominent men of the time; in additon to the ledger are numerous deeds and other documents involving Robert Morris.
1 volume, 80 p.; 56 items.
North American land company
Volume 1
Box 1
Early American History Note
This large bound contains a few records of stock sales and transfers for the North American Land Company, which had Robert Morris as one of its main investors. Interestingly, John Fries, leader of Fries Rebellion in Northampton County, purchased shares in 1795.
Biographical/Historical note
The North American Land Company was organized in 1795 by Robert Morris, John Nicholson, and James Greenleaf. The company speculated largely in unimproved lands all over the country.
Coxe, Tench, 1755-1824; FitzSimons, Thomas, 1741-1811; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823; Greenleaf, James, 1765-1843; Ingersoll, Jared, 1749-1822; L'Enfant, Pierre Charles, 1754-1825; Morris, Robert, 1734-1806; Muhlenberg, Frederick Augustus Conrad, 1750-1801; Nicholson, John, 1757-1800; Ruston, Thomas, ca. 1739-1804; Shoemaker, Benjamin; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841; Wilson, James,1742-1798.; Business Records and Accounts; Deeds.; Land and Speculation; Land companies -- Pennsylvania.; Land speculation; Real estate investment.
- Papers, 1768-1843; North American Land Company
  Scope and Contents note
  D. 56 items, 1 bd.vol, and 1 printed item. Various sizes.
  - Letter to Joseph Wharton, Jr., Philadelphia, July 16, 1768; 973 N75. 1; 12-1/2x7-3/4; Cornell, Samuel, 1731-1781
    New Bern, L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see N.A.Land co. Misc.papers, no.1.) Business.
  - Indenture to Barckly [sic] and Mitchell, June 6, 1774; 973 N75. 2; 13x8-1/4; White, Elinor
    Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: John Brig; witnessed: John Honan and Joseph Johns, Mayor. 1p. (see N.A.Land co. Misc.papers, no. 2.) On same document are sale of this indenture from Barclay and Mitchell to Davis Bevan; Sept.12,1774; and sale from Bevan to John Hubley;Aug.28,1776.
  - Sale of indenture of Elinor White to Davis Bevan, Sept. 12, 1774; 973 N75. 2; 13x8-1/4; Barclay & Mitchell
    D. Witnessed: Wm.Fisher. 1p. (see N.A. Land co. Misc.papers, no.2.) On same sheet as indenture of Elinor Shite to Barckly [sic] and Mitchell; June 6, 1774.
    General note
    Unlocated 5/2011
  - Sale of indenture of Elinor White to John Hubley, Aug. 28, 1776; 973 N75. 2; 13x8-1/4; Bevan, Davis
    D. Witnessed: Geo: Hubley. 1p. (see N.A.Land co. Misc. papers, no.2.) On same sheet as indenture of Elinor White to Barckly [sic] and Mitchell; June 6, 1774.
  - List of Georgia audits, Jan. 25, Feb. 16, 1785, 1790; 973 N75. 3; 18x15; North American Land Company
    D. 2p. (see N.A.Land co. Misc.Papers, no. 3.)
  - Receipt to Watson and Greenleaf for monies for Daniel Crommelin & Sons, Dec. 5, 1792; 973 N75. 4; 13x8, 19-1/2x8; Ludlow, Daniel, & Co
    New York, D. 2p.and end. (see N.A.Land co. Misc.papers, no. 4.) ----Copy.
  - A note on the pine land of Georgia., 1793 - 1795; 973 N75. 55; 15x9-1/2; Walton, George, 1749 or 50-1804 (Drawer Oversize)
    D. 24p.and end. (see N.A. Land co. Misc.papers, no. 55.)
  - Receipt to Watson & Greenleaf for monies for Daniel Crommelin & Sons, May 20, 1793; 973 N75. 5; 9-3/4x8; Ludlow, Daniel, & Co
    New York, D. 2p. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc.papers, no. 5.)
  - Deed to Robert Morris, June 6, 1793; 973 N75. 6; 13-1/2x8; Stoker, Margaret
    Printed D. filled in in ms. S. Witnessed: Jo[h]n Clymer and James Loughy. 1p.and end. (see N.A. Land co. Misc.papers, no. 6.)
  - Receipt to Jonathan Williams, Jan. 4, 1794; 973 N75. 8; 4x7; Morris, Joseph Benjamin W
    A.D.S. 1p.and end. (see N.A. Land co. Misc.papers, no.8.)
  - Deed to John Nicholson, Jan. 18, 1794; 973 N75. 9; 13-1/4x8-1/2; Morris, Robert, 1734-1806
    Printed D.filled in in ms. 1p.and end. Incompleted. (see N.A. Land co. Misc.papers, no. 9.) Contains also ms.form of deed which is incomplete.
  - Receipt to James Greenleaf for Georgia audited certificates, with list of same, Feb. 26, 1794; 973 N75. 10; 12-1/2x12-1/2; Dublois, Lewis
    D.S. 2p.,end. Copy. (see N.A.Land co. Misc.papers, no. 10.)
  - Deed to John Evringham, Aug. 2, 1794; 973 N75. 7; 12-1/2x8 and 11x16; South Carolina
    Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: Will[ia]m Moultrie, Peter Bremar, and Ja[me]s Workes. 2p.and end. Seal. (see N.A.Land co. Misc. papers, no. 7.)
  - Deed to John White, Sept. 1, 1794; 973 N75. 11; 22-1/2x20; South Carolina
    D.S.: Will[ia]m Moultrie; Peter Freneau, secretary, Peter Bremar, pro.Survr.Genl., and Clement Biddle, Not.Publ. 1p.and end. Parchment. (see N.A.Land co. Misc.Papers, no.11.)
  - Lease of lands in South Carolina to John Hall, Jan. 20, 1795; 973 N75. 12; 18x14-1/2; Brodie, Robert
    Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: Robert Brodie; Witnessed: D.R.Evans and M.Winn. Attest: F.W.Yongue,J.P. 1p.and end. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc. papers, no. 12.)
  - Account with Jonathan Williams, jr., March 3, 1795; 973 N75. 13; 6-1/2x8; Biddle, Clement, 1740-1814
    D.S.: Clement Biddle by Thomas Biddle. 1p.and end. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc.papers, no. 13.)
  - Receipt to Jonathan Williams, jr. for lumber, March 20, 1795; 973 N75. 15; 3x8; Britton, John
    Philadelphia, D.S. 1p.and end. (see N.A. Land Co. Misc.Papers, no. 15.)
  - Deed to William R. Reddock, March 27, 1795; 973 N75. 16; 10x8, 12x12; Georgia
    Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: Geo[rge] Mathers, governor; Edward Watts, and T. McCall. 2p.and end. Seal. (see N.A. Land Co. Misc.Papers. no. 16.)
  - Receipt to Jonathan Williams, June 3, 1795; 973 N75. 17; 3x8-1/2; Morris, Joseph Benjamin W
    D.S. 1p.,end. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc.papers. no. 17.) On same sheet is order to pay from Jonathan Williams to the Bank of Pennsylvania to W.Morris; June 3, 1795.
  - Draft on the Bank of Pennsylvania to [J.B.] W. Morris, June 3, 1795; 973 N75. 17; 3x8-1/2; Williams, Jonathan, 1750-1815
    A.D.S. 1p. (see N.A.Land co. Misc.papers, no. 17.) On same sheet as receipt from J.B.W. Morris to J.Williams; June 3, 1795.
  - Promissory note to James Greenleaf, Dec. 21, 1795; 973 N75. 18; 3x7 and 9-1/4x7-1/4; Morris, Robert, 1734-1806
    Philadelphia, D.S. 2p.and add. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc.papers, no. 18.) Concerning the North American Land Company.
  - Ledger, March 10, July 4, 1795, 1805; 973 N75. 14; North American Land Company
    Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: Rob[er]t Morris, et al, and witnessed by various persons. 239 leaves, of which 81 contain writing. Q. For references to W.T.Franklin, F.A. Muhlenberg, John Vaughn, etc., see index.
  - Promissory note to James Greenleaf, 1796 September 24; Nicholson, John, 1757-1800
  - Letter to Robert Morris, Philadelphia, Dec. 20, 1796; 973 N75. 20; 12x7-1/2; Swansey, William
    Washington, N.C., A.L.S. 2p.and add., end. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc.papers, no.20.) Concerning a canal on Morris' land and plans for expoloitation of the land.
  - Letter to Robert Morris, Philadelphia, March 4, 1797; 973 N75. 21; 9x7-1/4; Swansey, William
    Washington, N.C., A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see N.A.Land co. Misc.papers, no. 21.) Concerning N.A.Land co. speculation. Concerning the canal.
  - Receipt to Jona[than] Williams, July 3, 1797; 973 N75. 22; 4-3/4x5-1/4; Morris, Joseph Benjamin W
    Philadelphia, D.S.: "Recd Pay for B.W.Morris,Isaac W Morris." 1p.and end. (see N.A.Land co. Misc.papers, no.22.)
  - Promissory note to Joseph Brown from land speculation furnished by Robert Morris and James Greenleaf in the N.A.Land co, First Installment, Aug. 18, 1797; 973 N75. 23; 15-1/4x7-3/4; Pratt, Henry
    Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: Henry Pratt, Tho[ma]s W.Francis, Jo[h]n Miller, Jr., Jo[h]n Ashley and Jacob Baker. 1p. (see N.A.Land co. Misc. papers, no. 23.) ----Second Installment.
  - Receipt to J[onathan] Williams, Sept. 30, 1797; 973 N75. 24; 3-1/2x5-1/4; Morris, Joseph Benjamin W
    Philadelphia, D.S.: Tho[ma]s W. Weene for Benj[ami]n W. Morris. 1p.and end. (see N.A.Land company. Misc.papers, no. 24.)
  - Protest on non-payment of promissory note, drawn by Zach[aria]h Cox to James Greenleaf, Nov. 4, 1797; 973 N75. 25; 10x8; Biddle, Clement, 1740-1814
    Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: Clement Biddle, Not.Pub.; Witnessed: Alexander Murray and John Fisher. 1p.and end. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc.papers, no. 25.) Attempted to collect at the request of Mordecai Lewis.
  - Receipt to [Jonathan] Williams, Aug. 23, 1798; 973 N75. 26; 3-1/2x8-1/2; Fiss, Daniel
    D.S. 2p. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc.Papers, no. 26.)
  - Receipt to [Jonathan] Williams, May 11, 1799; 973 N75. 27; 5x6-1/2; Warren, Richard
    A.D.S.and countersigned by James Warren. 2p.,add.,end. (see N.A.Land co. Misc.papers, no. 27.)
  - Articles of agreement with John Adams for the farming of Mount Pleasant, May 17, 1799; 973 N75. 28; 15x9-1/4; Williams, Jonathan, 1750-1815 (Drawer Oversize)
    D.S.: John Adams, Jona[than] Williams; witnessed: Elizabeth Hewson and Grace Wagner. 3p.and end. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc.papers, no.28.) On same sheet is receipt from J.William to John Adams; Jan. 5, 1800.
  - Receipt to [Jonathan] Williams, 1799 July 10
  - Receipt to John Adams for stock, Jan. 5, 1800; 973 N75. 28; 15x9-1/4; Williams, Jonathan, 1750-1815
    A.D.S. 1p. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc.papers, no. 28.) On same sheet as articles of agreement between J.Williams and John Adams; May 17, 1799.
  - Proposed alterations and amendments to the original articles of agreement, addressed to Adonija[h] Stansbury, Dec. 31, 1802; 973 N75. 30; 15-3/4x10; North American Land Company
    Philadelphia, Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: Rob[er]t Morris, Jun[ior]. 1p.and add. (see N.A.Land co. Misc. papers, no. 30.)
  - Opinion as to the safety of Messrs., Dec. 20, 1806; 973 N75. 31; 12-3/4x7-3/4; Ingersoll, Jared, 1749-1822
    Nixon and Barclay in their parts as trustees of the N.A. Land Co.; D.S.: Jared Ingersoll, Edw[ar]d Tilghman, and M[ordecai] Lewis. 2p.and end.and broadside attached. Copy. 12-3/4x7-3/4. (see N.A. Land Co. Misc. papers, no.31.)
  - Letter to Henry Pratt, Philadelphia, June 21, 1809; 973 N75. 32; 10x8; Greenleaf, James, 1765-1843
    Washington, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see N.A.Land co. Misc.papers, no. 32.) Business of the N.A.land co. Refers to R.Morris.
  - Letter to James Greenleaf, May 13, 1813; 973 N75. 33; 9-1/2x8; Pratt, Henry
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p.and end. Draft. (see N.A.land co. Misc.papers, no.33.) N.A. land company business.
  - Letter to John Ashley, Philadelphia, March 9, 1814; 973 N75. 34; 10x8-1/4; Greenleaf, James, 1765-1843
    Washington, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see N.A.land co. Misc.papers, no.34.) N.A.land company business.
  - Letter to Henry Pratt, Philadelphia, March 13, 1814; 973 N75. 35; 10x8-1/4; Greenleaf, James, 1765-1843
    Washington, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc.papers, no. 35.) North American Land Company business.
  - Letter to John Miller, Philadelphia, Nov. 29, 1814; 973 N75. 36; 10x8; Greenleaf, James, 1765-1843
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc.papers, no. 36.) North American Land Company business.
  - Letter to Henry Pratt, Philadelphia, Dec. 4, 1814; 973 N75. 37; 10x8; Greenleaf, James, 1765-1843
    Washington, A.L.S. 2p.and add.and end. (see N.A.Land Company. Misc.papers, no. 37.) North American land company business.
  - Letter to Henry Pratt and John Ashley, Philadelphia, Dec. 12, 1814; 973 N75. 38; 10x7-3/4; Caldwell, Elias Boudinot, 1776-1825
    Washington, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc.papers. no. 38.) Business of Gillis Grenveldt with the North American land company. (John Greenleaf).
  - Letter to John Ashley, Philadelphia, Dec. 13, 1814; 973 N75. 39; 10x8-1/4; Greenleaf, James, 1765-1843
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see N.A.Land co. Misc.Papers, no. 39.) Business.
  - Letter to John Miller, Philadelphia, Dec. 15, 1814; 973 N75. 40; 10x8-1/4; Greenleaf, James, 1765-1843
    Washington, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see N.A.Land co. Misc.papers, no.40.) North American land company business.
  - Letter to John Miller, jr., Philadelphia, Dec. 19, 1814; 973 N75. 42; 10x8; Greenleaf, James, 1765-1843
    L. 1p.and add.,end. (see N.A. Land co. Misc.papers, no. 42.) Business.
  - Letter to Henry Pratt, Thomas W.Francis, John Miller, jr., John Ashley and Jacob Baker, Philadelphia, Dec. 19, 1814; 973 N75. 41; 10x8-1/4; Greenleaf, James, 1765-1843
    Washington, A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc. papers, no. 41.) North American land company business.
  - Letter to H[enry] Pratt and Thomas W. Francis, Philadelphia, Dec. 27, 1814; 973 N75. 43; 10x8-1/4; Greenleaf, James, 1765-1843
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see N.A. Land Co. Misc.papers,no.43.) Business.
  - Letter to John Miller, jr., Philadelphia, Dec. 31, 1814; 973 N75. 44; 10x8-1/4; Greenleaf, James, 1765-1843
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see N.A.Land co. Misc.papers,no.44.) Business.
  - Opinion of the legality of the supplements to the Yazoo Acts, April 10, 1815; 973 N75. 45; 13-1/2x8-1/4; Tilghman, Edward, 1750-1815
    D.S. 3p.and end. (see N.A.Land co. Misc.papers, no. 45.)
  - Letter to James Greenleaf, Jan. 26, 1818; 973 N75. 46; 9-1/2x8; Pratt, Henry
    Philadelphia, A.L.S.: H.Pratt for J[ohn] Ashley. 1p. and add.,end. (see N.A. Land co. Misc. papers, no. 46.) Business.
  - A list of Georgia audited certificates, May 28, 1823; 973 N75. 47; 15-3/4x13; Wereat, John
    D. 3p.and end. End.by H.King as agreeing with list of James Greenleaf. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc. papers, no. 47.) For additional information, see: H.King. List...; July 2, 1823.
  - List of Georgia Certificates, Undated
  - List of south Carolina indents., Undated
  - List of and receipt to James Greenleaf for Georgia audited certificates, July 2, 1823; 973 N75. 48; 12-3/4x8 and 7-1/2x6-1/4; King, Henry
    D.S. 4p. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc.papers, no.48.) For list, see: Wereat. List of Georgia...;May 28, 1823.
  - Affadavit regarding the Georgia certificates, Nov. 3, 1825; 973 N75. 49; 9-1/2x7-3/4; Greenleaf, James, 1765-1843
    D.S. 3p.and end. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc.papers, no. 49.)
  - Letter to William M. Tilghman, Philadelphia, July 12, 1843; 973 N75. 50; 10x8; Greenleaf, James, 1765-1843
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc.papers, no. 50.) Business.
  - Proposal for a lumber business., 973 N75. 53; 12x7-1/2; Cox, Zachariah
    D. 4p. (see N.A.Land Co. Misc.papers, no. 53.)
  - List of state papers received for D. Crommelin & Sons., 973 N75. 54; 6-1/4x7-3/4; Ludlow, David, & Sons
    D. 1p.and end. (see N.A. Land Co. Misc.papers, no. 54.)